<Document>
  # Citations and Sentencing
  
  <Box>
    [color=#999999][italic] The formal and necessary methods of formally enforcing Nanotrasen corporate law within the sector are detailed in this document. Failure to follow the protocols detailed below may result in the decisions of offending personnel being nullified, offending personnel being demoted, or criminal prosecution based on severity. [/italic][/color]
  </Box>

## Table of Contents

1. Fine Administration

2. Arrest Protocol

3. Sentencing Guidelines

4. Repeat Offenses

## 1. Fine Administration
For the purposes of jail time, 1,000 spesos is equivalent to 1 minute of jail time, allowing for appropriate substitution of penalties based on circumstance and station needs.

I and II degree crimes may be handled via on-site ticketing with the officer's signature at the issuing officer's discretion assuming the cited fine does not exceed 2,000 spesos. A copy must be provided to the offender and another retained for bookkeeping. If the fine exceeds $2,000 the offender must be processed at security by a sentencing officer.

Cargo personnel are prohibited from utilizing spesos to pay personal fines due to the inherent embezzlement risk. High severity crimes (IV-V Degree) mandate jail time and cannot be entirely compensated through financial penalties by any personnel.

Fine collection must follow strict accountability protocols: immediate logging in security records and prompt transfer to Command personnel for secure vault storage. Misappropriation of collected fines or pattern of excessive maximum penalties will result in bribery charges (CC, 4.A.2), immediate demotion, and asset forfeiture.

## 2. Arrest Protocol
[bold]2.1 Initial Approach[/bold]
Security personnel must approach suspects with clear identification of both themselves and the suspected offense, requesting compliance before escalating to physical restraint, except in circumstances of active threat.

Active threats are defined as suspects currently engaged in:

- Physical assault
- Weapon brandishing
- Sabotage in progress
- Escape from custody
- Any IV-V degree crime in progress

[bold]2.2 Force Authorization[/bold]
Progressive force protocols apply to all security operations:

[bold]Verbal Commands:[/bold] Primary approach for all non-active threats

[bold]Non-Lethal Force:[/bold] Authorized upon non-compliance with verbal commands

[bold]Lethal Force:[/bold] Authorized only when the suspect is:

- Actively fighting back with significant threat to the arresting officer
- Known to be armed with lethal weapons and demonstrating hostile intent
- Designated as an Enemy of the Corporation (RotA, 3)
- Presenting imminent lethal threat to other personnel

[bold]2.3 Processing Protocol[/bold]
Upon successful detention, suspects must be:

Transported to the Security department without delay

Searched thoroughly according to Search Protocol (RotA, 1)

Informed of all charges being considered

Provided opportunity for medical treatment if injuries are present

[bold]2.4 Legal Rights[/bold]
All detained personnel that are not Enemies of the Corporation (RotA, 3) maintain the right to:

Request legal representation from licensed legal personnel.

Demand formal trial proceedings for IV degree crimes or higher (Legal SOP).

Be informed of all charges against them before sentencing.

## 3. Sentencing Guidelines
All sentencing for arrested subjects is to primarily be handled by the Warden. If no Warden is available the HoS is to take over that duty. If there is no HoS it falls onto the highest ranking member of Security, and finally the Captain.

Use common sense and humanity when issuing citations or sentences. You should not always seek out the highest punishment you can, you don't have to always give the maximum time or always look to demote someone. Always take in account the severity and only charge for what is needed for someone to learn their lesson.

[bold]Stackable Crimes:[/bold] Crimes are to be considered 'stackable' in the sense that if you charge someone with two or more different crimes, you should combine the punishments additively. Linked crimes cannot be stacked, and are denoted with suffixes in Culpability and Criminality, you should pick the highest crime that matches the case.

[bold]Executions:[/bold] Executions may be authorized by the Captain or Head of Security after a trial has been conducted, or in the case of a Capital Crime. Executions may also be approved by CentComm, following formal contact.

[bold]Plea Deals:[/bold] Prisoners may negotiate plea deals in exchange for lighter sentencing, at the discretion of sentencing personnel. Plea deals may include providing information on accomplices, returning stolen items, assisting in investigations, or other services deemed valuable to Nanotrasen. The terms of any plea deal must be documented and may fully eliminate punishment for offenses up to III degree.

## 4. Repeat Offenses
Offenses repeated again after having been detained for the same crime can have more spesos added to the recommended maximum citation/sentence. The general guideline is as follows:

[bold]Second Offenses[/bold]

[bold]Recommended Increase:[/bold] Recommended to increase citation/sentence fine by 1.5x for the same crime only.

[bold]Third Offenses[/bold]

[bold]Recommended Increase:[/bold] Recommended to increase citation/sentence fine by 2.5x for the same crime only.

[bold]Further Repeat Offenders[/bold]

If the detainee has committed the same crime more than three times in separate occasions, it will be up to the Warden's, or in absence of a Warden, the highest ranking Security Member's discretion on whether they should be put into the Permanent Brig.

If the fine is greater than $20,000 and cannot be paid, permanent confinement is highly recommended, the debt will be addressed at CentComm.

  <Box>
    [color=#666666][italic]This section of Space Law has been reviewed for compliance with all relevant documents by S. Eclair, CentComm Legal Specialist.[/italic][/color]
  </Box>
  </Document>