<Document>
  # Rights of the Accused
  
  <Box>
    [color=#999999][italic] Those accused and those convicted of crimes aboard space stations retain certain rights regardless of circumstance, except those designated Enemies of the Corporation. These are to ensure frontier justice does not take hold in chartered Nanotrasen space, due to the difficulty to maintain profitability in such a state.[/color][/italic]
  </Box>

  ## Table of Contents

  1. Search Protocol

  2. Implantation Procedure

  3. Enemy of the Corporation

  4. Prisoner Treatment

  5. Parole Protocol

  ## 1. Search Protocol

  A personnel search is a seizure of the objects in a person's backpack, hands, coat, belt, pockets, and hat. If any contraband is found during a search the officer may choose to further the search into a detainment or simply confiscate the restricted items. After the search is conducted all legal items are to be returned to the person.

  [bold]Area Searches:[/bold] Security personnel may conduct searches of departmental areas, or areas reasonably expected to be private, for contraband or criminal activity. On Green or Blue Alert, area searches require a warrant issued by the Captain or respective department head without exigent circumstances.

  Non-incarcerated personnel may legally decline any search conducted without a warrant while the alert level is green.

  ## 2. Implantation Procedure

  Any prisoner in custody for a crime of III degree or higher can be subjected to implantation or implant removal procedures, so long as it's within reason. The process of adding an implant should not prolong the detainee's sentence, meaning you cannot hold them longer to administer the implant, unless stated below.

  [bold]General Implantation:[/bold]
  - A prisoner may consent to implantation or removal voluntarily.
  - Forced implantation requires incarceration AND one of the following:
    - [bold]Mindshields:[/bold] Suspected to be in an altered neurological state.
    - [bold]Trackers:[/bold] Charged with a IV degree or higher crime (CC, 4.D), classified as a severe flight risk, or known to use faux identities.
    - Other implants may also be pressed onto the incarcerated at the discretion of the Head of Security or the Captain.

  In the event there are individuals known to use brainwashing or otherwise neurologically altering devices to manipulate crew members beyond a shadow of a doubt, mindshields may be pressed on non-incarcerated personnel. Failure to comply with such an order is to result in a charge of endangerment (CC, 4.B.4), and personnel are permitted to be temporarily held in permanent confinement as more mindshields are procured.

  [bold]Removal Protocol:[/bold] Forced removal requires extreme evidence of an unauthorized implant, such as DNA on an expended implanter, or for events where there is no other possible explanation to some occurrence. Sentence delays/extensions are permitted until compliance. Consent bypasses evidence requirements.

  ## 3. Enemy of the Corporation

  An Enemy of the Corporation is defined as any sentient creature meeting at least one of the following criteria:

  - Associated with the Wizard Federation.
  - Escaped permanent confinement.
  - Seeking destruction or conquest of the station and its personnel.
  - Pirates or those engaging in piracy.
  - Predating on sentient life, even cannibalistically.
  - Shown to possess or have used items capable of controlling the minds of station personnel.
  - Designated an Enemy of the Corporation as punishment for a crime.
  - Designated an Enemy of the Corporation through a unanimous vote of the four highest ranked personnel on the station.
  - Known follower of religious practices unsanctioned by the Organization for Religious Exemptions.
  - Clones, Copies, or Replicas of currently living personnel.

  Enemies of the Corporation are not protected by spacelaw. They are to be captured and placed into permanent confinement if such does not risk the lives of station crew unduly and it is reasonable to assume they can be contained. They are to be brought to CentComm at the end of the shift if possible along with all other prisoners. If confinement is deemed unreasonable for any reason they should be executed promptly and without remorse.

  Enemies of the Corporation cannot be granted parole under any circumstances.

  ## 4. Prisoner Treatment

  Maintenance of incarcerated personnel is essential for preserving company investments and operational efficiency. Medical care must be provided with psychiatric and spiritual counseling available to optimize future productivity.

  Communication access via radio equipment shall be maintained unless demonstrably abused, as total isolation makes reintegration more difficult. Standard provisions, such as clothing, food, water, and cigarettes, should be provided to reduce psychological and physiological damage to the incarcerated.

  Legal counsel during interrogation preserves procedural integrity and minimizes potential litigation costs, and thus must be provided. Post-confinement, personnel must be reintegrated their shift mandated PDA and radio unless tampering is evident, in which case they should be administered anew at the office of the Head of Personnel.

  Freedom of movement within secure areas reduces long-term rehabilitation expenses. Restraints should only be employed when it's likely the incarcerated personnel will not comply or will be a threat otherwise.

  ## 5. Parole Protocol

  Parole is an arrangement with permanently confined personnel, allowing a return to station duties. Parole may come with any stipulations the Warden or other brig steward wishes, with a mandatory tracking implant and an expectation of compliance with all searches, regardless of alert level.

  A paper detailing the terms of parole must be carried by paroled persons at all times, bearing the signature of the paroled and the Warden's stamp. Paroled personnel must be handcuffed and confined on the evacuation shuttle to CentComm.

  <Box>
    [color=#666666][italic]This section of Space Law has been reviewed for compliance with all relevant documents by S. Eclair, CentComm Legal Specialist.[/italic][/color]
  </Box>
  </Document>